<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Christ-Church, Dublin, before both Houses of Parliament, May the 29th, 1661 being the anniversary of His Majesty King Charles the Second, his most memorable and happy restauration / by the Right Reverend Father in God, John Lord Bishop of Elphin.</title>
            <author>Parker, John, d. 1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13798465</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13798465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 470:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Christ-Church, Dublin, before both Houses of Parliament, May the 29th, 1661 being the anniversary of His Majesty King Charles the Second, his most memorable and happy restauration / by the Right Reverend Father in God, John Lord Bishop of Elphin.</title>
                  <author>Parker, John, d. 1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Blanden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dvblin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, XIX, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101877:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101877:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> DUBLIN, Before both Houſes of PARLIAMENT, <hi>May,</hi> the 29<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1661.</p>
            <p>Being the Anniverſary of his Majeſty King CHARLES the Second, his moſt memorable and happy Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>By the right Reverend Father in God, <hi>John</hi> Lord Biſhop of ELPNIN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DVBLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Bladen, Anno Domini</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:101877:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101877:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Thurſday, May <hi>30. 1661:</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <byline>By the Houſe of Lords.</byline>
            <p>ORdered that the Biſhop of <hi>Elphin</hi> ſhall have the thanks of this Houſe for his Sermon yeſterday, and that the Speaker doe give him the thanks of this Houſe, and that the Biſhop of <hi>Elphin</hi> be deſired to Print his Sermon.</p>
            <p>Copia vera.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John Keating,</hi> Deput, Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <head>
               <hi>30.</hi> May <hi>1661.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>By the Houſe of Commons.</opener>
            <p>ORdered that <hi>Cap. Trevor Lloyd,</hi> and <hi>Cap. Henry Nicholls,</hi> doe from this Houſe return thanks unto the right Reverend Father in God, the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Elphin,</hi> for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached at <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> the <hi>29.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, being the day of his Majeſties birth, and return unto his Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and to deſire his Lordſhip, that the ſame may be Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Copia vera.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Exam. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>Philip Fernely</hi> Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errat:</head>
            <p>Pag. 28. l. 14. pro <hi>operation,</hi> l. <hi>apparition.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101877:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101877:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. Sam. CHAP. 19. v. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he bowed the heart of all the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> even as the heart of one man, ſo that they ſent this word unto the King, Return thou and all thy ſervants.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even in the infancy of their Monarchy, and before the Tribes had unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtoop't to a divided Scepter, had yet the hard fate, (like theſe later Kingdoms) to be withdrawn from their due obedience to their natural Prince into a moſt horrid and unnatural Rebellion, and under the ſplendid notion of Reformation, to ſerve the baſeſt ends of luſt and ambition.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101877:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolom,</hi> whoſe aſpiring thoughts had ſwel'd his hopes to the expectation of a Kingdom, begins to quarrel <hi>Davids</hi> juſtice, and flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly bemoanes the people in the want of the executive part of it, that although their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were never ſo importunate of juſtice, yet there was none deputed by the King to hear them. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3.</p>
            <p>The way to mount himſelf upon the ſvvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wave of popular affection, he thought, was not directly, and at firſt, to tax the King of want of juſtice in himſelf, but his Miniſters, the want of able Miniſters, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute that juſtice which the King could not but neceſſarily beſtow; of which have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once poſſeſſed the people, they think none fitter to remedy the evil, then he that firſt found out the malady, and therefore are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to joyn with <hi>Abſolom,</hi> in his ambitious opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>O that He were made judge in the Land, that every man that hath any Suit, or Cauſe, might come unto him, and he would do him juſtice.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.4.</p>
            <p>'Tas been the ſly practice of aſpiring ſpirits, ſecretly to beſpatter his integrity, whoſe office
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101877:4"/>they cover, and to wound the Prince through the ſides of his Miniſters, and 'tis the jealous madneſs of the people many times to believe that juſtice vvill be done rather by any, than by him, vvhom God has (next unto himſelf) principally intruſted vvith the diſtribution of it. <hi>David</hi> (indeed) vvas a Prince, vvho had ſo large an intereſt in the affections of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that had <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſtruck point blanck, either at the office, actions, or perſon of the King, the people vvould have been ſtartled, as having their eares unaccuſtomed to any obloquies againſt the Lords Anointed; he finds fault therefore firſt, vvith vvant onely of perſons deputed to hear them, and vvhen once their eares are bored open, though but to collatteral aſperſions, they vvill at length be made tame, and obedient to more viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent invectives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolom</hi> having thus planted a jealouſie in the people, of the vvant of Miniſters under the King to execute juſtice, doth at length, (falling from his firſt pretences, though not firſt aim) labour to ſix them in this perſvvaſion, that the King himſelf vvas no friend unto ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101877:5"/>and ſo conſequently unfit to rule them. To ſuch a prodigious height of vvickedneſs, do the ſmall beginings of Rebellious evils grovv. The people could not vvant juſtice, as long as they had <hi>Darvid</hi> to judge them:
<note n="*" place="margin">Sal. de Guber. Dei Lib. 7.</note> 
               <hi>qui regit hocipſo quod regit judicat,</hi> ſays <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian,</hi> he that reigneth, even in that he reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, judgeth: and indeed vvhile <hi>David</hi> reigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> vve hear of no clamours of the people ecchoed forth for vvant of juſtice, till <hi>Abſoloms</hi> flattery, avvakens their jealouſies, and then like peccant perſons purſued onely by their own guilt, they ſtartle at each ſhadovv, and falſe appearance. But as ſoon as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> is driven from <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis of the Kingdom, and diſpovverd (as to the execution of his Regal authority there,) they ſoon find the vvant of that juſtice vvhich before vvas but abſent in a dream.</p>
            <p>The actions and concerns of Princes ſhould be tenderly dealt vvith, and 'tis dangerous to afford an open ear to any leſſenings, either of their Perſons, Actions, or Office; for by ſuch vvayes diſloyalty inſenſibly ſteals into the heart, which does but too frequently break
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101877:5"/>forth into open Rebellion in the hand. For thoſe, vvhich at the firſt follovved <hi>Abſolom,</hi> vvent out in their ſimplicity ſaith the text, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. <hi>ſimplicicorde,</hi> vvith a ſimple heart, they vvere men of a good meaning, little dreaming then of ingaging againſt the perſon and life of their King: they marched forth (at moſt, as 'tis probable) but as intentional Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for a publick diſtributive juſtice: I, but vvhen once the ſvvord is unſheathed, and that the people have in a perſonal (though perhaps not cordial) compliance, bidden open defyance to that ſacred power which they ſhould have religiouſly obeyed, they will rather by iterated acts of Rebellion ſeem to juſtify their firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, than by a timely repentance, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their guilt; ſo procreative is ſin, of ſin, that to juſtily the firſt, they neceſſarily involve themſelves in more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolom</hi> having thus by ſlie inſinuations, and ſpecious pretences, ſtolen the hearts of the People, and under the covert of Religion,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.7.8.</note> the pious payment of a vovv in <hi>Hebron,</hi> gained an opportunity to aſſemble his confederates, (as the fovvleſt actions are many times mask'd
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101877:6"/>vvith the faireſt pretences, and 'tas been the hard fate of Religion, to be but too common a cloak for Rebellion,) he then begins to take off the vizzard, and plainly diſcover, that 'tis not ſo much <hi>David's</hi> vvant of Juſtice, as <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom's</hi> vvant of the Kingſhip, is the religious cauſe novv to be contended for, and therefore <hi>Achitophel,</hi> vvho vvas his Mouth, as vvell as Oracle, delivers <hi>Abſolom's</hi> old ſenſe, but in a nevv, and plainer dialect. <hi>I will ſmite the King onely, and bring back all the people unto thee.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.2.3. Had the ground of the quarrell been onely vvant of Juſtice in <hi>Darvid's</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as vvas pretended, the deſigne (me thinks) ſhould not have been laid ſo cloſe to the perſon of the King; But this vvas but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, the other (it ſeems) vvas originally intended by the grand contrivers of the Plott: and yet vve find none of the people upon this early diſcovery, taking notice of the change, or returning unto their former obedience, upon alteration of the firſt ground of their engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but deſperately, novv proſecuting that intereſt, vvhich at firſt they abhorringly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ovvned: ſo dangerous are the beginnings of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101877:6"/>ſin, which being once tacitly admitted, hurry men on into the perpetration of thoſe crimes, which at firſt their conſciences would have trembled to have thought on. The people thus engaged, run headlong on to the Battel, and as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of the ſinners, <hi>their feet run to evil, and they make haſt to ſhed blood, Prov.</hi> 1 16. <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Abſolom</hi> pitch in the Land of
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.26.27.</note> 
               <hi>Gilead,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> and his men in <hi>Mahanaim,</hi> and both engage in the vvood of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> vvhere he, vvho is the great God of Battels and of recompences, gives a ſpeedy iſſue to their undertakings, for the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> vvere ſlain before the Servants of <hi>David,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.7.</p>
            <p>Succeſs in a bad cauſe, is ſometimes the worſt of puniſhments: had <hi>Iſrael</hi> proſper'd in that Rebellion, and had had the unhappy fate to have worſted their King, that ſucceſs (in their ſenſe,) would have legitimated the cauſe, and their proſperity (as judgeing by the event
<note n="*" place="margin">proſperum ac faelix ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus virtus vocatur, Senec. Tragad.</note>) would have made them baptize that a right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous cauſe, which in it ſelf was horrid, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, abominable. And indeed had they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper'd in that firſt encounter, 'tis probable they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101877:7"/>had not ſo ſoon (if ever) repented of the ſin: but almighty God giving ſo ſuddain a check to their unjuſt proceedings, that early rebuke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened their conſciences, and let them ſee the ſin in the puniſhment, which not onely put a ſtop to the growth of ſo dangerous an evil, but alſo moved them to return to their former obedience, which they manifeſted in their reſolution of bringing the King back to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> from whence his juſt fears, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by ſo general a defection of his people, had moſt unhappily driven him, <hi>and all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were at ſtrife throughout all the Tribes of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſaying, the King ſaved us out of the hands of our enemies, and he delivered us out of the hand of the</hi> Philiſtins, <hi>and now he is fled out of the Land for</hi> Abſolom. <hi>And</hi> Abſolom <hi>whom we anointed over us, is dead in battel: Now therefore why ſpeak ye not a word of bringing the King back?</hi> Ver. 9.10. In this great revolution, and eminent return of Loyalty, <hi>Iudah</hi> (it ſeems) was backward, and therefore <hi>David</hi> kindly invites them to the exerciſe of that obedience, which not onely the ready example of the other Tribes, but alſo the conſciouſneſs of their former guilt, might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101877:7"/>have prompted them to have performed, <hi>Ye are my brethren, ye are my bones and my fleſh, wherefore then are ye the laſt to bring back the King?</hi> Ver. 12. which gracious meſſage melts them into this ſweet and happy complyance, <hi>and he bowed the heart of all the men of</hi> judah, <hi>even as the heart of one man, ſo that they ſent this word unto the King, return thou and all thy Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words contain a Narration of the effect of King <hi>David's</hi> proffer of peace to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted, but novv returning People, namely, the invitation of their King to the repoſſeſſion of his Royal Crown and Dignity. In which likewiſe, theſe particulars offer themſelves to conſideration. 1. The perſon working, <hi>He.</hi> 2. The perſons wrought upon, <hi>the men of</hi> Judah. 3. The operation or effect, <hi>he bowed the heart of the men of</hi> Judah. 4. The extent, &amp; generality of this operation &amp; effect, it did not onely work upon ſome, and not work upon others, but upon <hi>all, he bowed the heart of all the men of</hi> Judah. 5. You have the conſent, unity, and harmony, which appears in this generality of operation &amp; effect, <hi>as the heart of one man,</hi> not diverſities of operations, making ſome obedient, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101877:8"/>others more ſtubborn and rebellious, like the Sun, which whilſt it ſoftens the wax, yet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens the clay, but as if the benigne aſpect had created new hearts, new tempers and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>He bowed the heart of all the men of</hi> Judah, <hi>even as the heart of one man.</hi> And laſtly, you have a farther conſequent, or effect of this bowing of their hearts, in that meſlage of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto the King, <hi>ſo that they ſent this word unto the King, Return.</hi> Now for as much as <hi>cauſa cauſae, eſt cauſa cauſati,</hi> the cauſe of the cauſe, namely of the inferiour cauſe, is the cauſe of the effect, namely, of that which flowes from the inferiour cauſe, <hi>David</hi> was the cauſe of their meſſage of <hi>return,</hi> in that he was the the cauſe by his firſt meſſage of bowing of their hearts, for had he not ſent unto the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Iudah, ſaying, why are ye the laſt to bring the King back to his houſe?</hi> Ver. 11. he had not bowed their hearts, and if he had not bowed their hearts, they had not ſaid, <hi>return:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before them in the proffers of Peace, it ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly melts them into their wonted loyalty and obedience, ſo that they ſent this word un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King, <hi>return thou.</hi> And that they might
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101877:8"/>fully manifeſt their love to their fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as well as loyalty to their Prince, they invite them too, to a participation of his joy, who had formerly ſhared with him in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>return thou and all thy ſervants, and he bowed the</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of theſe in their ſeveral orders, and firſt of the firſt, the perſon bowing, <hi>He, and he bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; He,</hi> that is, <hi>Sadock,</hi> ſay ſome; or <hi>he,</hi> that is, <hi>Amaſa,</hi> ſay others; or <hi>he,</hi> that is, <hi>David;</hi> ſayes a third; and ſo ſay moſt, and indeed ſo (allmoſt) ſay all, <hi>inclinavit ad ſe per ſuum benignum man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum,</hi> ſayes <hi>Lyra,</hi> referring to <hi>David,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc poteſt intelligi de David quod ipſe per ea quae miſit dici viris Judae per Sadock &amp; Abiathar ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinavit il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los totaliter, Toſtat, in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Tostatus</hi> to the ſame purpoſe that it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of <hi>David,</hi> bowing their hearts by that meſſage ſent by the high Prieſts. But the <hi>Chalde</hi> paraphraſe, as leaving it indifferent, reads onely, <hi>inclinatum eſt cor omnium virorum,</hi> that the heart of all the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> was inclined to their King, but who inclined, who bowed them, ſays not, but ſure, if we peruſe ſeriouſly the ſtory, we ſhall finde plainly and evidently, that 'twas <hi>David,</hi> though not without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentality of <hi>Sadock</hi> &amp; <hi>Amaſa.</hi> The perſon then working this great change in the men of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101877:9"/>
               <hi>Iudah</hi> (next under God) is <hi>David,</hi> and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail that he ſhould have ſo powerful an influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence over their hearts to turn them, when he had ſo juſt a tide &amp; authority over their perſons to rule them: being their King, Firſt, by God's particular deſignation, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. Secondly, by the joint choice of the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by their anointing him King in <hi>Hebron,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. and then by all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. But neither the ſenſe of their ſtill-due and oweing obedience, can ſo binde them, nor the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of paſt benefits, (for he ſaved them out of the hands of their enemies, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.9.) ſo engage them, but that they ſtrengthened the hands of an uſurper againſt their lawful Prince, ſo that he was conſtrained to flee out of the Land for <hi>Abſolom,</hi> till the return of providence ſo improved his condition, that he was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly invited to that place, from whence by their defection he was made exile. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God gave him an eminent and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able victory over his enemies, ſo that he cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that Cockatrice of Rebellion in the very ſhell, and might by a vigorous proſecution of that victory, have made their future obedience
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101877:9"/>the fruit of his ſword, and founded an after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty in the price of their blood, yet chooſes rather ſweetly to invite them to their duty, than compell them, to draw them with
<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 11.4.</note> bands of love, than with armies of violence, that ſo they may be ſaid to be active in their loyalty, not to ſoffer it.</p>
            <p>Kings you know, are frequently digniſyed with the title of
<note n="*" place="margin">Exo. 22.26 Pſal. 82.1.6. Joh. 10.34.</note> Gods in Scripture, not onely becauſe they are unto their reſpective people, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was unto <hi>Aaron, * Exod</hi> 4. <hi>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Dei,</hi> inſtead of God, but alſo becauſe they ought to imitate that God whoſe Majeſty in their office they ſo much perſonate and repreſent. Now goodneſs, mercy and kindneſs, being proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wherein the divine Majeſty delights moſt to ſhew it ſelf; Kings the more they exerciſe of theſe, the more clearly doe they evidence their ſimilitude, and likeneſs to that God, whoſe place they bear, and whoſe greatneſs they repreſent. God you may ſee in holy writ, frequently inviting his people upon their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral defections to return: ſo he does <hi>Iſrael, Iſai.</hi> 31.6.
<note place="margin">Jeremiah 3. Ver. 12.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Turn ye unto him from whom the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>have deeply revolted,</hi> ſo he does to <hi>Iudah,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101877:10"/>Ierem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 12.6. Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lz. 12.13</note> 18.11. <hi>Return ye now every one from his evil way:</hi> and though he be the party wrong'd, and highly injur'd, yet firſt ſpeaks of peace, and proffers reconciliation, inviting them to turn to him by repentance and obedience, that ſo he may return to them in the exerciſe of mercy and loving kindneſs. And thus King <hi>David</hi> in this ſtory, though the party wrong'd, highly injur'd, driven from his Pallace and Royal Throne, by a Rebellion of his own people, yet as imitating that God, whoſe vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent he was, does himſelf make the firſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertures and proffers of peace, moving them to invite him to a return, that ſo the reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of him in his Throne might be an act of their own revived loyalty, not the effect of the ſword as the ſcourge of their former diſloyalty and diſobedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hatſoever things were written aforetime,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> (ſays S. <hi>Paul.</hi>) <hi>were written for our learning:</hi> and ſurely then, if God being <hi>loeſa Majeſtas,</hi> the Majeſty highly injured, and provoked yet firſt proffers peace, and <hi>David</hi> though a King, and as groſſly injured, as ungratefully deſerted by his Subjects, yet in imitation of that merciful
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101877:10"/>God, firſt proffers reconciliation, we ought to follow the great exemplar of God and the King, and to be forward in our proffers of peace and love. The wiſdom, ſayes S. <hi>Iames,</hi> which is from above is firſt pure, and then peaceable, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.17. abhorring contentions, and full of peace and love, ſo that there is not a greater ſigne of pure and ſpiritual wiſdom, than hearty defires, and earneſt endeavours of peace: and therefore the author of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> bids us <hi>follow peace with all men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> and S. <hi>Peter,</hi> to <hi>feek peace and enſue it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.11.</note> and 'tis not ill writing after ſuch copies, nor unſafe to tread in thoſe pathes, which God himſelf has walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in before us: to be forward in proffers of peace, to thoſe that have wrong'd us and been our enemies cauſleſs, this is Prince-like, this Saint-like, Nay, this is God-like too, for ſo the Allmighty to his backſliding People, and ſo King <hi>David</hi> here to his revolted Subjects; which is the next particular, the Perſons wrought upon, <hi>the men of</hi> Judah.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that he calls the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, his bones and his fleſh, Ver. 12. and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101877:11"/>that they ſtyle themſelves near of kin unto the King, Ver. 42. but nearneſs of relation with ſome ſort of men, is no obligation to loyalty; for not onely they, that had eaten of his bread, but they alſo that were his near kindred, his brethren, his bones, and his fleſh, lift up their heeles againſt him: and ſurely it muſt needs wound the ſoul of a good Prince, and adde much grief to the preſſure of his ſorrows, when not onely the remoter ſort of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but even thoſe, which either nature, or his own bounty had made nearer unto him, ſhall ſeek his ruine, and attempt his life. This made <hi>Caeſar</hi> yield himſelf a willing Sacrifice, when he ſaw <hi>Brutus</hi> in the Conſpiracy: and therefore <hi>David</hi> aggravates his own miſerie, and the deplorableneſs of his condition, by the perfidiouſneſs of his friends, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.14. <hi>If it had been an enemy, then I could have borne it:</hi> that is, with more eaſe, and leſs <hi>dolor, but it was my familiar friend;</hi> this made it more inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſuch calamities, as theſe, ſtick cloſeſt, and wound deepeſt, and continue longeſt, and are moſt ſiguall: and therefore when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is interrogated, what were thoſe wounds
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101877:11"/>his hands, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.6. he replies, Ver. 7. <hi>thoſe wherewith</hi> I <hi>was wounded in the houſe of my friends:</hi> and the Spouſe in the Canticles ſeems to equal <hi>David's</hi> complaint, <hi>pugnaverunt contra me filij Matris meae, my Mothers children fought against me.</hi> And indeed when men for any ſecular, any by-ends or intereſt, act contrary to thoſe near tyes of relation; as their actions degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into the greateſt violences: ſo their former love into the greateſt hatred. For love, as it has a ready power of doing good, ſo likewiſe of doing hurt; which (me thinks) the Gentiles ſeemed vvell to repreſent, when they painted <hi>Apollo</hi> (by which they meant the Sun as the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick of love and beneficence,) holding in one hand an Harp, and in the other a quiver of arrows; (<hi>ubi amor ibi dolor,</hi>) ſhewing, that where harmony and love have been, there may be the greateſt hatred and confuſion. The other Tribes were (it ſeems) already become ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of their ſin, and had made publick mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of their forward inclinations to their Princes Reſtauration; onely <hi>Iudah,</hi> which had the neareſt relation, and ſtrongeſt obligation, is moſt backward; which backwardneſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101877:12"/>meets with a juſt check, Ver. 11. <hi>why are ye the laſt to bring back the King unto his houſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudah</hi> was the firſt that ſolemnly owned <hi>David</hi> for their King, and teſtifyed that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement by anointing him in <hi>Hebron,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. But now they are moſt backward in reſtoring him to thoſe rights, to which they themſelves were primarily inſtrumentall to give him title. The reaſon of this backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> is variouſly conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured: ſome think it was becauſe <hi>Abſolom's</hi> men had ſtill a guard in the Fort of <hi>Zion,</hi> and therefore they durſt not call the King back, leaſt by an unſeaſonable diſcovery of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, they might incenſe the rebellious par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſo, provoking their enemies rage, might haſten their own ruine: others appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the cauſe of this backwardneſs to be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the conſciouſneſs of their own guilt, and fear of the King's future revenge: but for this, you may ſee <hi>David</hi> paſſing an Act of Oblivion in his firſt overture of Peace, not calling them Rebells, or uſing any reproachful or reviling ſpeeches, but mildely, <hi>my brethren, my bones and my fleſh.</hi> And truly I am apt to believe, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101877:12"/>the conſciouſneſs of their own guilt was the greateſt obſtacle: they thought they had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beyond the King's mercy, and ſo durſt not truſt him: and indeed when men once appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend themſelves paſt pardon, they grow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, and labour to maintain and juſtify their former wickedneſs by continued acts of violence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudah</hi> of all the Tribes had the neareſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the King, and the Inhabitants of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> the greateſt benefit by his preſence, and perſonal abode among them, and therefore to be the firſt countenancers of the Rebellion, muſt needs be an aggravation of their ſin above that of others: but as there is no ſin ſo great, but God's mercy can forgive, ſo there is no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſo eminent, but the clemency of a good Prince can paſs by, which is plainly evidenced in <hi>David,</hi> for <hi>Iudah's</hi> offence had aggravation from their nearneſs of relation to the King, from their ingratitude for great benefits receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King, but none of theſe are mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, onely propoſalls of peace and love, which makes that Tribe overlook all difficulties, and ſo mollifies their obdurate hearts, that they are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101877:13"/>preſently melted into an happy complyance with their Prince, teſtifyed by the unanimous inclination of all their hearts unto him, which is the next particular, the operation or effect, <hi>he bowed. VVhere the word of a King is, there is power:</hi> ſays the Preacher, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.4. and ſurely 'tis from that Majeſty that God has ſtamped upon them, as the largeſt and livelyeſt images and repreſentations of himſelf, that their words are ſo operative, ſo powerful: <hi>David,</hi> vvhen he was but in election to be King, and before the Crown of <hi>Iudah,</hi> or <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had kiſſed his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred temples, is yet ſaid to have ſtayed his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with his words when they would have cutt off <hi>Saul</hi> in the Cave, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.7. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fregit viros,</hi> ſo the vulgar Latine renders the word, he brake them with his words, and the word in the originall ſignifies as much; to break, or to divide: and if his words were ſo povverful, vvhen onely the private unction had marked him out to be God's, much more povverful ſurely muſt they be vvhen he vvas knovvn by all <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be their King, and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally inſtated in the Throne of Sovereignty, to vvhich that Royal Character and ſacred ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101877:13"/>had formerly given him title. The Latine tranſlations generally read, <hi>inclinavit, he inclined the heart of all the men of Iudah,</hi> and that incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation implyes a bend of the mind, or heart, the people began to lean to their King, and their bovvels to yearne upon the ſufferings of their Prince, and indeed vvhere God's povver goes along, there can be no reſiſtance, there vvas an <hi>ero in ore tuo,</hi> to <hi>David</hi> here, as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4.12.</note> and ſo the voice of the King is the voice of God, and then, vvell may it bovv, and incline, and ſubdue all before it, for <hi>the voice of the Lord is powerful,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 29.4.</note> or, <hi>mighty in operation,</hi> and ſo is the voice of the King too, for <hi>whatſoever he commandeth them they do,</hi> ſaid he vvho vvrote the King vvas ſtrongeſt, 1. <hi>Ezdr.</hi> 4.3. vvhich is true here, for the King does no ſooner intimate his deſire, but they yield a ready and vvilling obedience, <hi>verbum Regis ornatum eſt poteſtate,</hi> and indeed, the povver vvas ſuch, that it vvas not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, vvhich is plain in the event, for <hi>they ſent this word unto the King, return thou</hi> &amp;c and it vvill not be unvvorthy of our obſervation, as vve paſs along, if vve take notice of the part
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101877:14"/>here ſpecified, upon which this povver had it's principal operation &amp; effect, the Text tells us 'tis <hi>the heart, he bowed the heart of all the men of Iudah.</hi> Kings may govern the bodies of their Subjects, and by their proper power ſubdue them, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs their hearts may be as rebellious, as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, as ever; but <hi>David's</hi> is a more Noble vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory than ſo, the Captives he takes are not the bodies, but the hearts of his People, <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid moſt true, <hi>inde poteſtas unde &amp; ſpiritus,</hi> for ſuch operations as theſe flow from no leſs a fountain than that of the Deity, and ſo that of S. <hi>Paul's, Rom.</hi> 13. is true in this ſenſe likewiſe, <hi>the powers that be, are ordained of God,</hi> and 'tis plain this was of God, when God-like it bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and inclined the heart: ſo that <hi>David's</hi> Throne now findes a ſurer foundation than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, being (in ſome ſimilitude and proportion) like that of <hi>David's</hi> Lord, and God's own Chriſt, ſeated in the hearts of his people.</p>
            <p>Many can beſtow upon their Prince the outward formalities of the cap and the knee, the voice and the tongue, bow before him, or ſay, God ſave the King, but all this while there is a <hi>nolumus hune regnare,</hi> in their hearts, they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101877:14"/>would not have the King Reigne over them; perhaps worſe; they would (had they power) deſtroy him! whereas their Loyalty ſhould be invvard, as vvell as outvvard, true and fincere, in the heart, and affections, as vvell as in the tongue, and outvvard actions. For as we ſhould give our hearts, firſt unto God, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire love and obedience: ſo next unto the King; the firſt is expreſs'd, the ſecond often implyed: <hi>my ſon, give me thine heart, Prov.</hi> 23.26.
<note place="margin">De Civitate Dei, Liber 15. Cap. 7.</note> This is in vvhich S. * <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerves vvas vvanting in <hi>Cain's</hi> Sacrifice, <hi>dans Deo aliquid ſuum, ſibi au tem ſeipſum,</hi> giving to God ſomewhat that was his, but giveing his heart, himſelf, unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: ſo doe too many, give ſomething of theirs unto God, ſomething perhaps unto the Ring, but give their hearts to themſelves, to their luſts and rebellious corruptions, nothing of it either to God or the Ring: whereas, (I ſay) they ſhould give their hearts to God firſt, and next unto the King: miſtake not the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I mean, in being really within vvhat they are ſeemingly vvithout; <hi>curſe not the King, no not in thy thought,</hi> ſayes the Preacher, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.20. and the vvord in the originall ſignifies any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101877:15"/>diſreſpect, or diſeſteem, and vvhere the vice is forbidden, the contrary virtue is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all bleſſing, reſpect, eſteem, love, loyalty, in our thoughts, in our hearts, unto the Ring; that's required of all, as here done by all; vvhich is the next particular, the generality of the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and effect: <hi>All the men of</hi> Judah, <hi>and he bowed the heart of all the men of</hi> Judah.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the men of</hi> Judah. <hi>Iudah</hi> of all the Tribes vvas the laſt that paid the tender of their duty and obedience: but being vvrought upon, by thoſe kinde meſſages and endearing ſvveetnel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes of the Ring, their converſion becomes more full, more univerſall, than the reſt of the Tribes; 'tis <hi>of all the men of</hi> Iudah. <hi>Nullus manſit qui non inclinaretur,</hi> not one diſſenting Brother among them. <hi>Sheba</hi> the Son of <hi>Bichri</hi> may blovv a trumpet of ſedition, and being angry at the departure of the Scepter from the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> and Tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> may, to gratify his ovvn ſpleen, engage the People in a nevv Rebellion, though it coſt him his head, <hi>but the men of</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah <hi>cleave unto their King,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.2. So that (me thinks) this Tribe is like that Son in the Parable,
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.28.</note> vvho being commanded by his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101877:15"/>Father to go and work in the Vineyard, ſaid he would not, but afterwards repented, and went. Thoſe whom the ſpirit of God, and the prudence and mildeneſs of reprovers have wrought to a true ſight of their ſins, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove moſt zealous, and conſtant in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the contrary graces: a converted ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is uſually moſt punctual, and intenſe in the acts of devotion, and a reclaimed Subject in the acts of loyalty and obedience: and good reaſon; for ſuch muſt make amends (as I may ſay) for their former deviations, and juſtifie to the world the ſincerity of their converſion by future acts of ſevere obedience to thoſe Laws, to which they had been formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious. See what reſtitution is proffer'd by <hi>Zacheus?
<note place="margin">Luke 19.8.</note> (Behold Lord the half of my goods I give to the poor, and if I have taken any thing from any man by falſe accuſation, I reſtore him four fold.</hi>) What love manifeſted by <hi>Mary Magdalen?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 16.1.</note> ſhe who had ſinned by unlawful embraces, you may find kiſſing the feet of our Saviour waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with her tears,
<note place="margin">Luke 23.56.</note> and wiping them with the hairs of her head; her love is ſtronger than death, and follows Chriſt to the grave
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101877:16"/>with prepared ſpices and oyntments;
<note place="margin">John 20.1.</note> her love prevents the day, and is more early than it at the Sepulchre: Oh, let us not then deſpiſe thoſe that have ſinned, but if they repent, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them; God does ſo, and the King does ſo; neither let us unworthily caſt any man's former ſin in his teeth, or revile him for doing ill heretofore, when as he does well now; but rather by all acts of kindeneſs, and ſweetneſs, encourage his preſent obedience, without any unhandſome reflections upon his former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty. To this purpoſe let us lay aſide all markes, and names of difference and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; this his ſacred Majeſty was pleaſed, as well to deſire as command, in his gracious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, Dated from <hi>Breda, Aprill</hi> 14. 1660.</p>
            <p>Alas, we have enemies enough, both to our Religion &amp; intereſt, at home, and abroad; let us not then by weakening our ſelves, give the enemy an advantage againſt us; which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly we ſhall doe, if we ſplitt again into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and revive any thing of our old animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities: but let us all endeavour to walk by one and the ſame Rule, to minde the ſame things: the glory of God, the peace and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101877:16"/>of the Church, the honour of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, the intereſt of the true Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the right of every honeſt, and innocent perſon in the Land: and let us doe this, not in word, and in tongue onely, but in deed, and in truth: in this, let us cry One and All; be as unanimous in this, as <hi>Iudah</hi> for <hi>David's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, let our hearts be <hi>as the heart of one man,</hi> which is the next particular, the conſent, unity, and harmony, which appears in this generality of operation and effect, <hi>quaſi viri unius, as the heart of one man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the ſpirit of God deſcended upon the Multitude of believers, <hi>Acts,</hi> 4.32. 'tis ſaid they vvere <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of one heart and of one ſoul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as ſome Copies adde,) and there was no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference among them; the holy ſpirit of unity knit their hearts in the unity of faith and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: and vvhen the pacifick meſſage of the King, as the ſpirit of an earthly and dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated Deity, was ſent to his rebellious Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; the ſweet influence thereof, fell upon their hearts, not onely, <hi>as the ſmall rain upon the tender hearb, but as the ſhowers upon the graſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.2.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101877:17"/>and not onely ſoftned the hard, and reduced the obſtinate, but allſo joyned the heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall, and united diſunited hearts, in the one <hi>point</hi> of love and obedience, and that <hi>tanquam viri unius, as the heart of one man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whil'ſt the People continued in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, they could not but ſuffer, under many a ſharp throw and pang of conſcience, which oftentimes like that hand writing upon the wall before <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.5.</note> changed their very countenances, and looſened their joynts, their midnight-thoughts ſtartling their black ſouls with the frightfull remembrance of their guilt; and the operation of their ſin, (like <hi>Hector</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aeneas,</hi> 
               <q>In ſomnis ecce ante oculos moeſtiſſimus <hi>Hector</hi> viſus adeſſe mihi)—</q> left ſuch a damp and horror upon their ſpirits, as was equal to that of thoſe viſions of the night, recorded, <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.13.14. Stung with theſe ſharp apprehenſions, both of ſin, and puniſhment, they were many times ready to have cryed out with that Jaylor, <hi>Acts,</hi> 16.30. <hi>VVhat must we doe to be ſaved?</hi> but thoſe better motions were ſuddainly expell'd;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101877:17"/>in ſome, by deſperate thoughts, (like thoſe of <hi>Cain,</hi>) that their ſin was greater than could be forgiven: in others, by pleaſing reflections upon their nevv purchaſed vvealth, they had bought much Land, (no matter though it vvere vvith the price of blood,) and therefore they cannot, they vvill not come: but vvhen God interpoſes his povver, and brings home the Ring's gracious meſſage, and proffer of peace, unto their hearts, they melt like ice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Noon-day Sun, and ſmoothly glide into the ancient Channell of their vvonted Loyalty and obedience. And as the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited them to the performance of their dutie, ſo they invite him to the repoſſeſſion of his Royall Crovvn and Dignity, <hi>they ſent this word unto the King,</hi> which is the next thing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the happy conſequent of this bovving of their hearts, vvhich is the calling of the King home to the exerciſe of his Regall povver and authority, vvhich is the very ſumme of this Text, and the great buſineſs of this day, <hi>return thou.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The People vvearyed vvith oppreſſion and confuſion, (vvhich are the undoubted conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101877:18"/>of Rebellion; and convinced of their ſin, by their happy unhappy ſucceſs, and the no common death of the Uſurper, call back their King: <hi>they ſent this word unto the King, return thou.</hi> And ſure I am, this was an happy meſſage, both for King and People: by his return, both were freed from thoſe dangers, and hardſhips, which were, (and allwayes are) the moſt certain attendants of warr. And indeed his long abſence made his return more wellcom, both to himſelf, and his Subjects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it made his Crown ſit leſs weighty on his own head, and his Government leſs burdenſome on the ſhoulders of his People. Some are taught to prize bleſſings beſt in the want oft hem.</p>
            <p>Would you underſtand the ſweets of a ſoft bed and gentle repoſe?
<note place="margin">Prov. 7.16.17.</note> of a morſell of bread, and a draught of wine? ask not the effeminate perſon, or rich glutton, ſuch as <hi>deck their beds with coverings of tapeſtry, with perfumes of Myrrhe, Aloes, and Cinamon, which
<note n="*" place="margin">Amos 6.4.</note> stretch themſelves upon their Couches, and eat the Lambs out of the Flock, and Calves out of the midſt of the ſtall; that
<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 16.9.</note> fare ſumptuouſly</hi> every day? but ask the labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, and weary travailer, the hungry, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101877:18"/>the thirſty ſoul, and they'l tell you: for our joyes are often heightned by our ſorrows; and we had not been many times ſo happy, had we not been ſo miſerable. The very afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this life make Heaven it ſelf more Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, and in this ſenſe too,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>work for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory,.</hi> God is therefore pleaſed many times to let us taſte the ſweetneſs of one condition, in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of an other; and to change either vvhen he thinks fit: for he who can turn the heart, can at his pleaſure, likewiſe alter the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Look upon King <hi>David</hi> but four Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before this of my Text, and you ſhall ſee him fleeing from <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> for fear of the Conſpirators,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.14.30.</note> weeping as he goes up the aſcent of Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> bare foot, and his head un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd. At <hi>Bahurim, Shimei</hi> curſes,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.5.6.</note> and caſts ſtones at him, and the heart of the men of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> are generally after the Uſurper, as you may read, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.13.</p>
            <p>Look upon him again, in this and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Chapter, and you ſhall ſee his enemies defeated, the purſuers purſued, the Uſurper hang'd, <hi>Shimei</hi> begging pardon, and the hearts
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101877:19"/>of the people after their King; inviteing him to that place, and exerciſe of that authority from both which they had ſo lately driven him. <hi>They ſent this word unto the King, return thou,</hi> and as they manifeſted their Loyalty in this to the Ring, ſo, their kindneſs in the next to their fellow-Subjects. <hi>And all thy Servants, return thou and all thy Servants.</hi> Which is the laſt thing in the Text, of which very briefly.</p>
            <p>And truly this kindneſs is well meaſured out by the line of Juſtice; that they that ſhar'd with him in the ſorrows of his exile, ſhould likewiſe taſte of the ſweets of his return. This was according to S. <hi>Paul's</hi> pattern for better things, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, acon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorification for a copaſſion, <hi>if we ſuffer with him, that we may be glorifyed together, Rom.</hi> 8.17. And the ſame Apoſtle tells the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chap. 1.29. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not onely to believe, but allſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> And ſurely to believe in Chriſt, is not onely an honour, but allſo an advantage; but to ſuffer for Chriſt, is a tranſcendent mark of favour. And truly (next to our ſufferings for Chriſt, and for Religion,) no ſuffering can
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101877:19"/>be more honourable, than for Subjects to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for, and with their King: Heaven it ſelf looks upon ſuch with an auſpicious eye, an eye of favour and regard. What wounds they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in ſuch a cauſe, are not brands, but marks of honour; a lim thus loſt, is not a want, but an addition, and to be look'd upon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Theophyl. in Gal. 6.17</note> as <hi>Theophylact</hi> in an other caſe, as ſome Trophe, or Regal Enſigne. Well then may they be invited to return with the King, who had thus hazarded their lives, and left all to follow the King: who had made good in their practice, what that <hi>Gittite</hi> profeſſ'd unto <hi>David,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.21. <hi>In what place my Lord the King ſhall be, whether in death or life, even there alſo will thy ſervant be,</hi> who had a love to his Perſon, as well as a duty to his Office; 'tis fit that theſe, all theſe, ſhould return: <hi>return thou and all thy Servants.</hi> And 'tis much you'l ſay, that they did not except ſome; ſome, as evil Counſellours, or unjuſt in the late management of their reſpective offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſo they might have put a better colour upon the face of their Rebellion; No, they are more ingenious in their repentance than ſo;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101877:20"/>they doe not by any meanes labour to extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their ſin, or to make loyalty a crime in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when Rebellion is pardoned in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but without any exceptions, <hi>return all, return thou and all thy Servants.</hi> And thus I have done with my Text, I ſhall begge your patience for a word or two of application, and ſo diſmiſs you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origen,</hi> being to preach on that of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt's, <hi>unto the wicked ſaith God, what haſt thou to doe to declare my Statutes? Pſal.</hi> 50.16. wept over his Text inſtead of preaching: and truly I may well weep over this Text, inſtead of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying; for that's many times a paſſionate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of joy, as well as of ſorrow; and we may juſtly call up the moſt ſignal expreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to evidence the greatneſs of our joyes, ſince this day my Lord the King came again in peace unto his own houſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not lead your attention into the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell and application, as I did into the ſtory of the Text, through the many contrivances and managements of the Rebellion, and ſhevv you hovv our Sovereign became an exile from theſe Kingdomes, as <hi>David</hi> from <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:101877:20"/>this were to rake in the dunghill, or to open <hi>Pandoras's</hi> box, and ſo infection might flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. His ſacred Majeſty hath graciouſly buryed all theſe in the Act of Pardon and Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, and I ſhall not preſume to unſeal the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre: but ſhall begin my application of the ſtorie, with the Text.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty having early notice of the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning of a Parliament to convene in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, Aprill,</hi> 25. 1660. and that the Lords were to be owned in that juriſdiction and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which did alwayes belong unto them by birth-right, and the fundamentall Lawes of the Land, he ſent two letters by a perſon of honour and integrity, together with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Declaration to all his Subjects of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or quality ſoever, to be firſt ſeaſonably communicated to both Houſes, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the whole Kingdom: in which Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Declaration, you may ſee ſuch meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſuch mercy and forgiveneſs, as might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily convince the world that he had a ſpirit ſuitable to that of <hi>David's:</hi> he ſvveetly mindes them of his own, and the Kingdomes ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and then call's for their duty and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:101877:21"/>
            <p>In his Declaration, <hi>least fear of puniſhment,</hi> (to uſe his Majeſties own words,) <hi>might engage any to a perſeverance in guilt for the future, by oppoſing the happineſs and quiet of their Country, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of King, Peers, and People, to their juſt, ancient, and fundamental right;</hi> He granted free and generall Pardon to all, of what quality, condition, or degree whatſoever, that within forty dayes after publication thereof, ſhould take hold of that his grace and favour (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as the Parliament ſhould except.) Such, who having waſhed their hands in the Sacred blood of his Royal Father, were not capable of Pardon. Nor could thoſe Nobles and worthy Patriots finde out a readyer vvay to expiate that horrid Crime, and avert thoſe heavy judgements, which then threatned the Nation, than by an exemplarly execution of thoſe unparalell'd Regicides.</p>
            <p>Theſe Letters and Declaration, ſent to both Houſes, being publiquely read, produced the like effect, vvhich that meſſage of King <hi>David's</hi> did on the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> they <hi>bowed,</hi> they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined the hearts of the People unto the King; and were, indeed, the firſt appearance of our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101877:21"/>long expected happineſs, and the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all this our enſueing peace. For up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reading of theſe Letters &amp; Declaration, both Houſes of Parliament, (the great repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of the Kingdome,) paſſed this Vote, (or to this effect, as near as I can remember,) that his Majeſty CHARLES the Second, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon the death of his Royall Father of bleſſed memory, as true and lawfull Heir, was the undoubted King of theſe Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>See how God, who turnes the heart, can change the condition. 'Tis not many yeares ſince, vvhen each new Parliament produced a new Vote againſt the King; their chief work being, by all the Lawes they could contrive, to diſable him from claiming, and frighten the people from promoteing him unto the Crown: to this purpoſe the Uſurper begot Parliaments, and upon them Ordinances, with which they quickned ſo faſt, (ſometimes to a ſuperfetati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;) that a ſecond was haſtily begotten, before the firſt was born. But novv they freely, and vvithout danger, Vote, and publiquely ovvn him their lavvfull and undoubted King, whom even novv, had been Treaſon but to have named vvith honour.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101877:22"/>
            <p>The day, wherein theſe gracious Letters and Declaration, were read in Parliament, vvas the firſt of this Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> in the year 1660. And truly this Moneth, ought to be unto us as <hi>Abib</hi> unto the <hi>Iſraelites, Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>the beginning of Moneths.</hi> Their deliverance from <hi>Egypt's</hi> bondage being not more ſignall, than this of our's, from the bondage of thoſe cruell, bloody, and uſurping Tyrants: Perſons, of whom I may moſt truly ſay, as <hi>Gregory Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi> ſaid of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, they had the defection of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> the cruelty of <hi>Ahab,</hi> the hardneſs of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the ſacriledge of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> adv. Julian.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Nay, a complication of all impieties in one.</p>
            <p>The firſt day then of this Moneth was the birthday of our happineſs; and each ſucceeding day, was the happy Parent of new joyes. <hi>Dies diei eructat verbum, Pſal.</hi> 19.2. <hi>Day unto day uttered ſpeech, and night unto night ſhewed know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> For not long after this publique own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the King, the Houſes ſent Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to invite him home; being much more impatient of his ſtay, than others had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly fearfull of his arrivall; <hi>they ſent,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101877:22"/>they ſent again, <hi>this word unto the King, return thou</hi> &amp;c. And here again, you may behold a change indeed. Not many yeares ſince you might have ſeen your King, forced to diſguiſe himſelf in the poor habit of a mean Servant, to eſcape the fury, and rage of his bloody, and rebellious Subjects; and in that diſguiſe, to ſeek relief and ſhelter in forreign Countries, where their kindeneſs was ſeldom longer lived than their advantage; and, when he was not aptly ſerviceable to their ends, they vvere no more charitable to his vvants. They who were his own allyes, bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, unkindely deſerted him; and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the Vſurper, denyed him the benefit of their ayr to breath in: ſo that like <hi>Noah's</hi> Dove,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 61.3.</note> he ſcarce found reſt for the ſole of his foot.</p>
            <p>Yet in the Crovvd of all theſe temptations, nothing could ſtagger his faith, or make him ſvverve from the true Proteſtant Religion: and therefore God hath now given him <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for aſhes, the oyl of joy for mourning, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſs.</hi> Yea,
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 21.2.</note> God <hi>hath given him his hearts deſire, and hath
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101877:23"/>not denyed him the requeſt of his lips,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 21.7.</note> why? <hi>becauſe the King truſted in the Lord, and through the mercy of the moſt highest, he did not miſcarry,</hi> but upon the 25. or 26. day of this Moneth, his Majeſtie landed at <hi>Dover,</hi> and the 29. (this day, which vve novv celebrate,) he made his entrance into his renovvned City of <hi>London,</hi> to the unexpreſſible joy, and ſatisfaction of all his good People.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, never vvas there a people ſo overwhelmed with joy, neither ever vvas there a people more expreſsive of their joy and loyall affections: conducting his Majeſtie, into that his Royall City in far greater ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and triumph, than any one of his moſt victorious Predeceſſours, Kings of <hi>England,</hi> return'd from their greateſt Conqueſts. So that they that bragg'd of their ſignal Conqueſts, might have here beheld a Conqueſt indeed, a victory Royal, one like that of <hi>David's,</hi> fit for a King, ſo many thouſand hearts taken captive in one day.
<note place="margin">Exod. 7.12.</note> This victory, like <hi>Aaron's</hi> * rod, has ſwallowed up all their victories, and like <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh's</hi> Magicians they muſt novv confeſs, <hi>digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Dei eſt hic,
<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 8.19.</note> this is the finger of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:101877:23"/>
            <p>And truly, I eſteem it the greateſt tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall happineſs I ever yet enjoyed, that I vvas an eye-witneſs of that joy, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I could not vvell diſtinguiſh, whether the teares trickled faſter from the eyes, or the acclamations ecchoed lowder from the mouthes of the People.
<note place="margin">Num. 23.21.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord their God was with them, and the ſhout of a King was among them.</hi> All former <hi>Crucifige's</hi> vvere now turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the loudeſt <hi>Hoſanna's:</hi> and though teares trickled down, yet were they not <hi>lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae doloris,</hi> but <hi>lachrymae amoris,</hi> not teares of ſorrow, but teares of love, ſo that I could not but take up that obſervation, which the Jevves did of Jeſus, when he vvept over <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus: Ecce quomodo amabant eum,
<note place="margin">Iohn 11.36.</note> behold how they loved him.</hi> Sure I am, the ſpirit of God moved upon theſe waters.</p>
            <p>This day then (of us never to be forgotten) his Majeſty enter'd upon the actuall poſſeſſion of his Royall Crown and dignity: this day <hi>he
<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 19.30</note> came again in peace unto his own houſe; and</hi> and vvith him (as vvith <hi>David) all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants;</hi> many worthy Gentlemen, and Nobles;
<note place="margin">Duke of ORMOND.</note> and among them, one, vvho (having ſome
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101877:24"/>yeares under his Majeſty governed this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,) loſt his eſtate, and often hazarded his life, for the preſervation of thoſe whoſe falleneſs (to ſay no vvorſe,) made him an exile, and themſelves (but juſtly) ſlaves to an uſurping povver: Perſons, vvho could ſigne Letters of renevving obedience to day, when as by excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications denounced againſt him, &amp; all that ſhould adhere to him, they had councermand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it the day before; as if they intended to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedate their own apoſtacy, and let the vvorld ſee, (vvhich is ſtrange) that their relapſe, was more ancient than their repentance: of theſe things my eyes have been but too ſad vvitneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. As for thoſe that have conſtantly adhered to his Majeſty, and his intereſt, as they have allready taſted of his Princely bounty and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, ſo I hope they ſhall of your juſt care. <hi>Conſumetur nequitia peccatorum, let the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the wicked come to an end, but eſtabliſh the juſt, Pſal.</hi> 7.9. I remember it vvas the ſaying of that Noble perſon upon a publick occaſion (to vvhich ſome here I believe can bear vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs vvith me) that <hi>it was more honourable to ſuffer with the beſt of Princes, than to live glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101877:24"/>with the worſt of men.</hi> He verified this in his practice and conſtant adherence to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and that vvithout any ſiniſter or by-ends, but meerly conſcience to God, and duty to his Prince And I bleſs God he is novv return'd again, return'd an example of Loyalty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy to poſterity. And (I hope I may ſpeak as vvithout ſuſpicion of flattery, ſo likevviſe of offence,) this vvhole Nation may bleſs God too, I am ſure this Church may, I am ſure it does: and as vve all bleſs God for, and joy in, his Majeſties return; ſo is our praiſe height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and our joyes enlarged by his return vvith ſuch Servants, <hi>return thou and all thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There remains one thing more, and that is a pious, cordial, and thankfull remembrance of the moſt ſignal mercies of this day. A day, not to be paſſed over in ſilence; but a day to be celebrated with the greateſt expreſſions of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and joy we can imagine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herodotus</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">Herodotus Lib. 9.</note> that the <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings had allwayes a ſtanding officer with a <hi>memento</hi> for them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And indeed, our own gratitude ſhould be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101877:25"/>that ſtanding officer, to put us frequently in minde of the great matters of this day; for the more ready performance whereof, let me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort every one of you in thoſe words of the Lord unto the Prophet. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.2. <hi>Son of man write thee the name of the day, even of this ſame day.</hi> Our Sovereign Lord King CHARLES the Second, after twelve yeares expulſion from his Kingdomes, returned to the poſſeſſion of his Crown and Royall dignity <hi>this ſame day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> A day, fit to be written, not onely with a pen of Iron, or point of a Diamond, but with a Quill borrowed from the wing of ſome glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Cherubim: God himſelf has writ it with a beam of the Sun, in ſuch glorious and reſplendent mercies, that he that runs may read it. Oh, let us write it too, write it upon our hearts in the indeleble Characters of pious and religious thankfullneſs. The Children that are yet unborn, and the generations which are yet to come, ſhall bleſs God for this day; this day, which was the reſtauration of our King, of our Church, of our Religion, of our Laws, of our Liberties, of all that we can call vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, good, honourable, or ſacred.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:101877:25"/>
            <p>This day has in it a double feſtivall; 'tis the day of his Majeſties moſt happy Birth and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and 'tis the day of his Majeſties moſt happy reſtauration; very well expreſſed by the Act of Parliament for the perpetual Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary Thankſgiving on the 19. of <hi>May: the moſt memorable Birth-day, not onely of his Majeſty, both as a Man and Prince, but alſo as an actual King, and of this, and other his Majesties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</hi> I may ſay then with <hi>David,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.12</note> this is the day which the Lord hath made.</hi> Aſſuredly it was his doeing, and it is marvellous in all men's eves. Let every one then in a grateful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the bleſſings and mercies of this day, ſay with <hi>David, quid retribuam Domino? what ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits towards me?</hi> Let us take the cup of Salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord, let us pay our vovves unto the Lord, novv in the preſence of all his people: and let us all humbly implore the riches of God's mercy, vvho is the fountain of all our joyes, that he vvould gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly continue the joyes of this day unto us; that neither vvenor our Poſterity may ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the like ſad confuſions. To this end, let
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101877:26"/>us pray, that God would continue his Majeſty upon his Throne, the Church in her poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Religion in it's purity, the People in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and theſe three Kingdomes in a firme and durable peace. For the better effecting of all this, let us pray, pray, not from the lip onely, but from the heart and ſpirit: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ivat Rex,</hi> let the <hi>King</hi> live, let him live long, let him live happy; and laſtly, that the Soul of our Lord the <hi>King</hi> may be bound up in the bundle of life with the Lord his God, let us pray fervently, pray ardently, pray conſtantly, yea, pray as <hi>David</hi> danced before the
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 6.14</note> Arke, <hi>even with all our might. Domine ſalvum fac Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</hi> GOD SAVE THE KING. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101877:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
